For somebody who's tuned into this point, they're in that category of metabolic dysfunction. They have some
extra weight to lose, but they're inspired and they're going to take action.
For somebody that's going to adopt a lot of we talked about today, what do you recommend? Jumping in cold turkey and
just doing everything or doing it at a slower pace and letting their body adjust?
>> It depends how ill you are. and you know I see people with fatigue syndromes and some of them are very ill because
when you put in place these interventions you get detox reactions, you get ketogenic hypoglycem
you get keto flu.
sometimes if you're you know allergic to food you can get you know allergy and addiction are two sides the same
coin. You can get withdrawal symptoms.
So if you're otherwise completely well and I'd use just jump in and do it. But if you are sick, I think you have to do
it more slowly. And the other point here is if if people have been running on carbohydrates for all their life and the
most the vast majority of people have, then they will often struggle with a
highfat diet. And the reason for that is that the business of digesting fat is
enormously demanding of energy. The pancreas has to produce a lot of enzymes and the business of generating enzymes,
it requires a lot of energy. And so if that person has been running on carbohydrates for for ever and a day,
then they're just not going to be able to produce the enzymes to digest that fat. So sometimes you just have to
go into it slowly and maybe take extra pancreatic enzymes and maybe take some bile salts to help emulsify the fat
in order to facilitate, you know, fat that you can tolerate that fat. But so it the answer is it depends and the
sicker you are, the slower you go. For somebody that is very enthusiastic, they
jump in, they're very committed, how quickly can they turn this around?
>> Oh, very quickly. You know, in a in in a in a few days or weeks. As soon as you
get into ketosis, everything just starts to fall into place., you your blood
vessel your blood levels, you know, level out. You stop spiking insulin and and adrenaline. The brain settles
down. Your quality of sleep improves.
the fermenting guts. So if you've got any gut symptoms, they disappear and it's the starting if you've got any
condition associated with inflammation and I think much inflammation is driven by allergy to microbes in the upper
fermenting gut. Then the inflam inflammatory markers settle down and in parallel with this you know put in place
the detox regimes because we're all poisoned MSM and maybe metal collalation therapy. You know I'm increasingly
coming to the view that we all have to do it all. Now, when I started work as a
GP in the 19 early 1980s, it was relatively easy to get people well with a simple elimination diets and a few
supplements. Nowadays, it's much more difficult. It's much more difficult because because most people are
carbohydrate addicts. We're all poisoned., underactive thyroids and poor adrenal functions are and poor
mitochondrial functions are very common.
So, you know, you know, we just all have to do it all. And it always starts with diet and sorting out the upper
fermenting gut and taking a basic package of nutritional supplements and then playing it by ear from there on. If
you've got something, if you've got nasty pathology like cancer, then we haven't got time to muck about. You just
have to dive in you know and and do the keto diet ASAP because
you can't afford to waste time whilst
the cancer grows. As you know the difference between cancer cells and normal cells is cancer cells can only
run on sugars and carbs. whereas our immune system which is what we need to fight cancer that can run very happily
on fats. So it very much depends on the pathology. But these interventions
really are the starting point to treat absolutely everything.
>> For somebody that wants to throw everything at this. How do you feel about some of these newer tools that are
popular in the health world right now like methylene blue creatine anything
else in that realm that has a lot of momentum that people can stack on? Well,
creatine is very good for muscles and again keeping strong is very
important. So yes I'm very happy for people take creatine and for many it helps energy delivery mechanisms.
Metalene blue I would wouldn't do that straight away. yes it's a very safe intervention. It's good for energy
delivery mechanisms and it's you know it's it has good antimicrobial activity.
So so for some people that is very helpful too but people are always
looking for the quick fix and they come to me and they they want me to say you take this herb or you take that
methylene blue or you do this and you'll be fine. It's not like that. It's hard work and you know we're talking the
talk but that poor person then has to go away and walk the walk and actually do
it. So I try to concentrate on
what I call the bleeding obvious and you know we must all do the basics and for the vast majority of people all this
basic stuff done really well gets you an awful long way but better than that it
as I call it it clarifies those muddy clinical waters because people come to me with shopping lists of symptoms and
sometimes I don't know if this is going to cause that or if that's going to
cause the other but when you put in place all these interventions then cause
and effect becomes much more obvious and and then people then become their own doctors. They become their own
detectives because being a doctor should be like a detective. Then we get the symptoms which are our clues and then we
put in place various interventions and see if those symptoms improve. If they don't improve, we've got the diagnosis
wrong. We have to go back to base. But doctors don't think like this. They
don't think causation. And so what you know it's important to is we all have to
become our own doctor. We all have to be interested in self and nobody's going
to be better motivated and nobody's going to be in a better position to do it than self because there's only one
person that puts food in your mouth.
There's only one person that does your shopping and your cooking. and there's only one person that observes
those symptoms. And you know you know I after four and a half decades of of of
of going up every blind alley possible you know I'm now descending on the bleeding obvious and we all need
to do that and that will get the majority of people an awful long way.
Well, I think in conversations like this, we have to be careful along the lines of what you're saying, not to make
it too costly if we don't have to and not to make it too complicated because people are just going to turn an eye and
not get started. So, let's take it the other way as our final question here.
The opposite of bringing in things like methylene, blue, and creatine. What is the simplest formula for people? We've
shared a lot here over the last 90 minutes. I'm sure ketogenic diet is going to be the foundation, but what is
the simplest protocol somebody can adopt today?
Correct. To get that momentum.
>> Well, ketogenic diet and then take vitamin C and iodine to sort out the upper fermenting gut because that is so
common.
>> And if you've got an upper fermenting gut, then you will malabsorb nutritional
supplements. So, ketogenic diet, iodine and vitamin C to sort out the up fermenting gut. Then we all need a basic
package of nutritional supplements which a multivitamin a good multi-mineral
vitamin D 10,000 IU a day vitamin C 5 grams a day iodine lugal iodine three
drops which you already started on and then timerestrict eat consume all your
food within a six-h hour window of time and if you've got the energy in parallel with that you know we all need to be
strong we all need to do some exercise which benefits in so many ways PH and you don't have to do be a jogger. Just
simple isometric exercises that should become part of our daily routine
and that all that done really well is get going to get the vast majority of people a long way. Keep it simple. Oh, a
big pardon. And we should be doing detox regimes. Think heavy metals and MSM
for the heavy metals and then some sort of heating regime. So if you're a runner then just going for a little jog and
showering off afterwards. Fantastic. If you're not a runner, Epsom salt bars, fantastic., and we can all do that.
So, these are all things that can be incorporated into our everyday life.
They are the most frictionless interventions I can think of, and all
affordable, all intrinsically safe. The potential for harm is effectively zero,
and, just essential for us all to do.
>> If you enjoyed that clip, you're going to want to head over here and catch the full episode. I'll see you over there.
For insulin to work, it's got to have some essential co-actors. Things like
chromium, carnitine, vitamin B3, and vitamin B1. We can have insulin
resistance because the insulin receptor is blocked by something.